dialogues models or pop-ups whatever you
want to call them is something that
every front-end developer will
eventually have to build implementing a
model manually isn't Fun you have to use
either plain JavaScript or jQuery or
react combined with CSS to hide the
model then put it on the center you need
to obscure the background while the
model is showing you need to prevent the
user from scrolling and so on or you can
use the dialogue HTML element which is
already supported by all the major
browsers with the dialog element
building a model takes no time and
almost no JavaScript and CSS code
whatsoever let me show you here we have
a button followed by the dialog element
but as you can see only the button is
visible to the user the model is hidden
by default to open the model we are
going to grab both the button and the
dialog from our JavaScript we are going
to list listen for clicks on the button
and when I click happens we are going to
call the method show model on our dialog
and that's it now as you can see when we
click on the button the model will show
up on the center of the page on top of
the button it will obscure the
background as well and it will stay at
the center of the screen even if the
user Scrolls the model will also be
automatically closed when the user
presses the Escape key to create a close
button in our model we will put a form
inside of our dialog with the method
property set to dialog as you can see
when we click the button the model
closes it works out of the box without
any extra JavaScript which is great
let's add another button to our model
this time with a value of confirm and
let's give a close value to our close
Button as well to know which button the
user clicked we're going to go back to
our JavaScript and there we are going to
add an event listener to be notified
when the model is closed and inside of
the listener we will console log a
property of our model called return
value which is the value of the button
that the user clicked and as you can see
back in our console we can now know
which button was clicked that was so
simple just 10 lines of JavaScript code
and we have a model with buttons and all
if you want to change the color of the
background when the dialog is open you
can do so by using the backdrop sudo
element on CSS we can go for a darker
color or for a completely different
color we can also style the dialog
element directly in our CSS like on this
code where we remove the Border give it
a shadow and zoom around the corners
making our model look very very nice I
hope you enjoyed this video and I hope
that you found the dialogue element
useful as you can see browsers are
getting so much better and we can
accomplish so much without writing that
much code we still need JavaScript but
thankfully JavaScript is very easy to
learn especially if you take our free
Javascript 4 beginners course where we
spend 8 hours learning JavaScript
together and where we build things like
clocks to-do lists weather information
geolocation and more to join just click
the link below enroll for free and I
will see you there oh no though
see you on the next one I go down
[Music]
thank you